Hello, AR students.
Here's the fourth period in
just three minutes.    The
fourth period
begins in
1800 with the election of
America's first Democratic-Republican, Thomas
Jefferson.  He
believed in a strict
interpretation
of the Constitution,
limited federal
power, and an economy
based on
agriculture.  And in 1803,
Jefferson
approved the
Louisiana Purchase, which
doubled the territory of the
United States.
Foreign policy
dominated much of
Jefferson's presidency,
as he was
forced to respond
to the Barbary
pirates and the
Chesapeake and
Leopard incident.  And, like
Washington and Adams
before him, he was
dogged by
constant conflicts
between England and
France, leading
to the passage of the
Embargo Act of 1807.  And
although it was intended to
protect
American
industry and
maintain neutrality
, it hurt the
American
economy.  Next
was James Madison,
who served two
terms and led the
country during the War of
1812.  It was waged
through the
British's forced recruitment of
American
sailors and the
British military
presence in
western forts.
This war
saw the burning of the
White House,
the creation of the Star-Spangled
Banner, and the Battle of
New Orleans.  And the
Hartford
Convention,
led by Federalists
who opposed the
war, led to the
collapse of the party.  The war
ended in 1814 with
the signing of the
Treaty of Ghent.  Elected in
1816, James Monroe
ruled during a period of
prosperity and
national unity
that followed the
War of 1812.  And his
presidency
is often called the "Era of
Good Feelings"
because there was
only one political
party—Democratic-
Republicans.  Monroe
became famous for his
doctrine, which
warned
European powers
not to interfere in the
affairs of the Western
Hemisphere.  He
was also president when
Henry Clay's Missouri Compromise was passed
to maintain a
balance between free
and slave
states by
establishing the
36/30 line.  But the "Era of Good
Feelings"
ended with the "
corrupt bargain"
in the election of John
Quincy Adams in
1824.  The early 1800s
saw the
expansion of
democracy through
universal
suffrage for white
men,
allowing Democrat
Andrew Jackson to become the
first
"common man" president in
1828.
Jacksonian
democracy and
Jeffersonian
democracy were
similar in that
both supported an
agrarian nation and
states' rights, but
opposed a
National Bank.
But
Jackson's presidency was
extremely
controversial because of
his wars with
national
banks and the forced
relocation of
Native Americans, which
led to the "Trail of
Tears."  Another
major controversy
during the
Jackson administration was the
Nullification Crisis, when
John Calhoun of
South Carolina
refused
to abide by the Tariff of
1828, known as the "
Tariff of Abominations."  Now
, in response to
Jackson's policies, the
Whig Party was formed under the leadership of Henry Clay.  The Whigs
supported a strong
central government and the
growth of the
American
economy through
trade and
manufacturing.  This was
supported by
Henry Clay's "American System,"
which advocated
protectionist
tariffs, a second
national bank, and
internal improvements
.  Now the fourth
period also
focuses on the
market revolution.
Textile factories
like Lovell Mills
thrived with
the invention of the power
loom
and the spinning jenny.
These factories also
employed
unskilled
workers, such as
women, immigrants, and
even children.  And while
northern factories
were implementing
Eli Whitney's interchangeable parts, southern
plantations
were using his
cotton gin to
greatly increase
cotton production.
Meanwhile, Western
farmers
used the
steel plow and
mechanical reaper
to till
hard soil.  This
coincided with a
transportation
revolution that
united the nation.  New
steam engines
led to
the creation of railroads,
and Robert
Fulton's steamboat, the Erie Canal, and the
Cumberland
Railroad further
connected regional
economies.  The rapid
changes following
industrialization
also coincided with the
Second Great
Awakening.  Leaders
like Charles
Grandison Finney
held large
camp meetings, and
churches saw a
surge in
attendance.
New
denominations were also formed, such as the
Mormon Church.  This
wave of religious
enthusiasm inspired
social and
moral
reform movements
known as the
pre-civil
reforms.  Many
spoke out against the evils of
slavery within the
abolitionist
movement, such as Frederick
Douglass and William Lloyd
Harrison.  And groups like the
Women's
Christian Temperance Union
reformed to
speak out against
alcohol use.
Women also
gathered to
fight for equality
and suffrage,
such as at the
Seneca
Falls convention, where they drafted
the Declaration of Sentiments.
This movement was led by
women such as Elizabeth
Cady Stanton and
Lucretia Mott.
Social
movements also emerged to reform
hospitals, prisons, and
education.  Thanks for
watching, and if you
need more
help with APUSH, like
tutorials,
timelines, and
review videos,
be sure to
check out the ultimate review
packet.